Finding Aid for Leland Stowe papers, 1926-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leland Stowe papers 1926-1990
Stowe, Leland, 1899-
1.7 linear foot
85400 Aa 2
Journalist, free-lance writer, radio commentator, and professor of journalism, University of Michigan, 1956-1969. The collection contains copies of newspaper clippings, correspondence, articles by and about Stowe, and photographs of Stowe and his wife. The materials document Stowe's coverage of the Spanish Civil War and the resulting FBI surveillance of him, his coverage of World War II, his work for Reader's Digest, and his career as a University of Michigan journalism professor. The collection also includes poetry and biographical prose by Stowe.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in 1987 and 1993. Donor no. 6530.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Winner of a Pulitzer Prize in 1930 for his coverage of the 1929 Paris Reparations Conference, Leland Stowe became one of America's best-known foreign correspondents for his coverage of World War II. Stowe was born in Southbury, Connecticut on November 10, 1899. After graduating from Wesleyan University (Worcester, Massachusetts), Stowe began his journalistic career. He was foreign correspondent for the New York Herald Tribune from 1926 to 1939. During this time, Stowe published his first book, Nazi Germany Means War (1933). When the Herald Tribune told him he was too old to cover World War II, Stowe left for the Chicago Daily News, where he was war correspondent from 1939 until 1943. Stowe continued his war coverage with ABC radio and the New York Post Syndicate.
In 1952, Stowe married Theodora Calauz, a woman he had met at an embassy meeting in her native Hungary in 1940. During the postwar years, Stowe held numerous positions, including two years as director of Radio Free Europe's News and Information Service. In 1955 he became a roving editor for Reader's Digest, and in 1956 he joined the University of Michigan as a professor of journalism. Thus, he enjoyed a dual career, teaching part of the year and working for the Digest for the rest of the year. In 1969, Stowe retired from the university; his affiliation with Reader's Digest lasted through 1976.
Leland Stowe died in 1994.
This collection contains copies and clippings of Stowe's writings, articles about Stowe and his career, and documentation of Stowe's years as a University of Michigan professor. Stowe pulled these materials together for the Bentley quite self-consciously. Although most of Stowe's original papers are maintained in a collection at the Mass Communications History Center of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, this collection is notable for the annotations made by Stowe and for his selection process. It also contains small amounts of original correspondence.
Subjects:
Journalists--United States.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Stowe, Leland, 1899-; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Stowe, Leland, 1899-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Articles. 1936-1972
  The Articles series (1936-1972) contains articles written by Stowe, especially during his years as a roving editor for the Reader's Digest.
  - Part 1: Researched & Written on Assignment for The Reader's Digest, circa 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - Part 2: Articles in Reader's Digest, circa 1952-1969 (Box 1)
  - Part 3: Not Published by The Reader's Digest, Although Accepted, circa 1952-1972 (Box 1)
  - Part 4: Not Published by The Reader's Digest, Although Accepted, circa 1959-1972 (Box 1)
  - Random Selection circa 1936-1970 (Box 1)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation
  The Federal Bureau of Investigation series (1937-1986) documents FBI surveillance of Stowe brought on by his coverage of Spain before and during the Spanish Civil War; the series includes clippings, correspondence, FBI documents, and articles by Stowe.
  - "Between the Crossfires: The Case History of a Foreign Correspondent and Writer Investigated by the FBI," circa 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - "Between the Crossfires, Vol. II" circa 1938-1986 (Box 1)
  - "Between the Crossfires from Right-Wing and Left-Wing Extremists: The Case History of a Liberal Correspondent and News Commentator Investigated by the FBI," circa 1937-1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Regarding FBI Case File circa 1980-1986 (Box 1)
- Personal
  The Personal series (1926-1988) contains biographical articles, poetry (mostly to his wife), correspondence, and photographs (black and white, as well as photocopies of black and white photographs).
  - Biographical circa 1943-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General circa 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - Selections from Stowe's Letters (bound) 1926-1979 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous Quotes/Verses/Articles Collected by Stowe circa 1959-1971 (Box 1)
    - Perera, Padma--writings 1962 (Box 1)
    - Regarding former student circa 1987 (Box 1)
    - Travel 1955-1981 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Stowe and wife, circa 1939-1989, 2 folders; black and white prints (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Lecture, "The Meaning of the Soviet-American Crisis," February 8, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Poetry circa 1927-1988 (Box 1)
    - Prose circa 1950-1987 (Box 1)
    - Reviews of Stowe's Book The Last Great Frontiersman ( 1982 ), 1983 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan 1956-1990
  The University of Michigan series (1956-1990) contains materials relating to a "foreign assignment" used by Stowe in his journalism classes, the Leland Stowe Journalism Essay Award (established at the University of Michigan in 1982), and Stowe's retirement from the university.
  - Foreign Assignment (assignment for Stowe's students) 1956-1969, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - The Leland Stowe Journalism Essay Award circa 1977-1990, 3 folders; 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - While a Professor: To My Students (Valedictory [April 1969] and Some Lectures) 1958-1969 (Box 2)
  - Souvenir of April 10, 1969 the University of Michigan Department of Journalism's Leland Stowe Day--On the Occasion of his Retirement as a Professor (Box 2)
  - Valedictory to Stowe on "L.S. Day," April 10, 1969 (Box 2)
- World War II
  The World War II series (1933-1976) contains clippings and copies of Stowe's writings about the war (including his journals), articles about Stowe's journalistic exploits, and occasional correspondence.
  - Nazi Germany Means War (London: Faber & Faber, 1933 ), pre-war book by Stowe (Box 2)
  - No Other Road to Freedom (Knopf?), Stowe's World War II Journals: While Reporting the Russo-Finnish War from Finland (bound), December 1939-March 28, 1940
    - On the Greek-Italian front in Albania (bound) December 1940 (Box 2)
  - Reporting
    - Global Beats from Norway and Germany's Invasion, etc. 1939-1941 (Box 2)
      (includes later related materials, 1955-1976)
    - Chiefly Russo-Finnish War & Germany's Seizure of Norway 1939-1940 (Box 2)
      (includes later related materials, 1944-1984)
  - Second World War Comments, and Other Press Clippings (bound) 1940-1971 (Box 2)
Related Material
Most of Stowe's original papers are maintained in a collection at the Mass Communications History Center of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin.